Okay, so today's דף daf is קב. Kuf Bais. And we had
been talking about this issue of if שינוי מקום shinui makom צריך
לברך, tzorech l'varech, if when you change locations and you have to
make another ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. It started specifically with the issue
of wine. You made a קידוש kiddush on wine in one place,
you said בורא פרי הגפן, borei pri hagafen, you drank, let's even
say it was במקום סעודה, bimkom seudah, and then you went and
you wanted to continue drinking somewhere else. Do you have to make
another ברכה, bracha, which is a general ברכות brachos question, less of
a פסחים Pesachim
question. And there were different opinions. רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both
said you had to make another בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagafen.
רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan said you did not. We had a proof
from a ברייתא braisa against רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan said שינוי מקום
shinui makom צריך לברך, tzorech l'varech, you have to. And then the
גמרא Gemara made a distinction, had a debate between רב ששת Rav
Sheshes and רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna said that
you would only have to make another ברכה bracha if in the
new place, if you were not having in the first place a
meal that required a ברכה bracha in the same location, a ברכה
אחרונה bracha achrona like בענטשן benching or על המחיה al hamichya according
to most. Then, in that scenario, if that were the case, that
you were having a meal that required a ברכה bracha at the
end in the same place, then even if you went, somewhat ironically,
even if you went to a different place and continued drinking, it's
not considered a new experience. It's considered all, anyway, you're allowed to
come back to your old place to בענטשן bench anyway, and it's
all considered an extension of the primary eating that was done in
the first place. And in that case you do not require a
new ברכה. bracha. That was רב הונא's Rav Huna position as opposed
to under other scenarios you would when you switch places. And רב
ששת Rav Sheshes says regardless when you switch places you have to
make another ברכה. bracha. And the גמרא Gemara then had a proof
in a scenario that was not exactly identical, that was you switched
places and you came back. That's a case where you might think
that everybody says you don't have to make a new one, but
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara treated it as the same. And the case
was that people were sitting and they were drinking wine and presumably
as the גמרא Gemara assumes they were eating a meal, and then
they went out to go to שול shul or they went out
for חתן chosson and כלה, kallah, and when they come back do
they have to make a new ברכה bracha or not? So the
ברייתא braisa says they don't have to make a new ברכה bracha
if they left people behind. So the גמרא Gemara says look, it
sounds like without... A, it sounds like that they had uprooted themselves,
sounds like they were having a serious meal there, like המוציא, hamotzi,
and nevertheless the only reason they don't make a new ברכה bracha
is because they left people behind. So it sounds like against רב
הונא. Rav Huna. It sounds like under other circumstances you would always
have to make a new ברכה bracha once you switch locations even
if you were having bread and even as this ברייתא braisa seems
to say, even if you returned to the original place. So that's
where we left off where the evidence of this ברייתא braisa seems
to be that you have to make a new ברכה bracha once
you switch locations even in a case where you were having a
real fixed meal in the original location. Doug, you had a question?
Yeah, I was thinking about the entire discussion as you've just summarized
it, it's very much organized around the objectivity of place. Like in
this place, right in that place. I see תוספות Tosafos at the
bottom of עמוד ב, amud bais, קא עמוד ב kuf-alef amud bais
introduces הסח הדעת, hesach hadaas, which is that subjective category.
We
haven't raised that in this discussion at all. Is that something the
ראשונים Rishonim introduce into this, like that subjective element?
Yes, there is, and the phrase that you find often in the
ראשונים Rishonim and in another תוספות Tosafos is that part of this
position is that שינוי מקום shinui makom constitutes הסח הדעת hesach hadaas
by definition, which means, you know, you could interpret it as meaning
we assume
you're מסיח דעת masiach daas when you switch locations, on the fact
that you're eating. Like you lose the mindset of eating and therefore
when you decide to eat again it's a new experience.
I'm mean eating the whole time, like I'm eating my bagel...
I understand, which is why it seems more accurate anyway to read
it as it's an objective counterpart to הסח הדעת. hesach hadaas. The
same way הסח הדעת hesach hadaas creates a sense of discontinuity, so
שינוי מקום shinui makom also creates this objective sense of discontinuity, but
not that we're trying to argue that it really is a proof
of or an indicator of an actual
subjective
הסח הדעת. hesach hadaas. Look, the גמרא Gemara does not mention הסח
הדעת. hesach hadaas.
It's like if you stay in the same place and you fall
asleep.
Right, exactly, so sleep might be הסח הדעת. hesach hadaas. Or you
went to watch the football game and then you completely forgot about
your meal and then you wanted to go back and continue eating.
So the הסח הדעת hesach hadaas is a subjective reality of a
discontinuity with your eating, and the שינוי מקום, shinui makom, the issue
seems to be more of an objective one, which is why again
more formal and objective criteria like were you קובע סעודה koveia seudah
in this place might be able to come in and assist because
then it says things are seen more easily as an extension of
the primary eating that was done in the first place.
at that original סעודה, seudah, yes? I just got text messaged asking
are we doing livestream today?
We should be, go on Ustream and look for YCTorah. You know,
do a search for YCTorah and hopefully you will find it, yes?
Yes, just so I want to understand. According to this, even if
I'm like whatever it is I'm having. Like my you know I'm
having a Tootsie Pop and I go here and back and forth.
I'm eating my bagel the entire time. I never stop. I've gone
there, I've gone there, around my area and I come back whatever.
Right.
So there might be a difference there, but there is some actual
discussion that even if you're continuing to eat it, שינוי מקום shinuy
makom might require a ברכה. bracha.
Now, not washing your hands again.
Now again, no, well, okay. But let's I'm not going into all
the הלכה halacha but I do want to point out just as
a tie-in to Dov's point, is that the question is to what
degree does specific intent overcome the issues of שינוי מקום? shinuy makom?
And תוספות Tosafot does discuss, for example, by קידוש במקום סעודה, Kiddush
bimkom seudah, תוספות Tosafot discuss a middle, a middle place of not
מקום makom which is, you know, the roof and the floor of
the same building where תוספות Tosafot said there if you have it
in mind, it constitutes one place.
Means to go
to the roof, to go from the roof to the floor. To
go from inside to outside, having it in mind won't help. And
different spaces in the same room you don't need to have it
in mind, but in this middle type of different of scenario, it
would. So you could ask this question by by שינוי מקום shinuy
makom as well, the intersection between the subjective intent and the objective
reality. To what degree can positive subjective intent help? But let's move
on. So the גמרא Gemara says, we'll read the last line of
קא עמוד ב. kuf aleph amud bet. So קשיא לרב חסדא. kasha
leRav Chisda. So this ברייתא brayta that I just said to you
about uprooting and coming back, it sounded like they were having a
fixed meal and it sounded like with if they didn't leave anybody
behind, they'd have to make a new ברכה bracha when they returned.
So that's against רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and this is even when
they came back to the same place. So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak will tell you, top of קב עמוד א, kuf
bet amud aleph, מאן תנא עקירות רבי יהודה. man tana akirot Rabbi
Yehuda. No, no, no. Who is the author of that ברייתא brayta
about uprooting yourself and leaving people behind? That's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
But there's going to be a חכמים, Chachamim, a majority opinion, that
argues on him that says that you don't have to make another
ברכה. bracha. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in the
ברייתא. brayta. חברים שהיו מסובים. chaveirim she-hayu mesubin. So this is almost
exactly the same as the ברייתא brayta we just read. The first
part of it at least, or whatever, the second part about it.
חברים שהיו מסובים, chaveirim she-hayu mesubin, if you had a group that
were reclining, and basically means that they were having a meal. So
that's דברים טעונים ברכה אחרונה במקומם, devarim te'unim bracha achara bimkomam, something
that you would have to go back and make a ברכה bracha
and make a בענטשן benching in that place.
Not on Seder, for example.
No, no, no, no. Yeah, during on a Wednesday. ועקרו רגליהם לילך
לבית הכנסת או לבית המדרש. ve-akru ragleihem leilech le-veit ha-knesset o le-veit
ha-midrash.
And then they got up in order to go to שול shul
or to go to the
study hall. כשהן יוצאין אין טעונין ברכה למפרע, keshe-hein yotzin ein te'unin
bracha le-mafrea, they don't have to make a ברכה, bracha, you know,
on what they had already eaten. וכשהן חוזרין אין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה.
u-keshe-hen chozrin ein te'unin bracha le-chatchila. And
when they because they're planning on coming back, so why don't bother
בענטשן benching now, don't worry, you'll come back. And when you come
back, you don't have to make a new המוציא hamotzi and then
you'll just finish eating and then you'll make a ברכה bracha at
the end. Now, אמר רבי יהודה. amar Rabbi Yehuda. By the way,
some of the ראשונים Rishonim point out that the חידוש chiddush of
אין טעונין ברכה למפרע ein te'unin bracha le-mafrea is also that we're
not concerned that you might come to forget that you might forget
to come back. So maybe we would say yes, if you do
come back you won't have to בענטשן bench again, but maybe we
would insist you בענטשן bench before you leave because you might forget
to come back. Okay? But I guess, but anyway so that's how
they understand part of the חידוש. chiddush. But either way we see
you don't have to make either a בענטשן benching or a new
ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona when you return. אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi
Yehuda, said רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda: במה דברים
אמורים? bamei devarim amurim? When is that true? בזמן שהניחו שם מקצת
חבריהם. bizman she-hinnichu sham mikzat chaveireihem. If they left some people behind.
אבל לא הניחו שם מקצת חבריהם, aval lo hinnichu sham mikzat chaveireihem,
if they didn't leave people behind, כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע, keshe-hen
yotzin te'unin bracha le-mafrea,
when they leave they do have to make a ברכת המזון. Birkat
Hamazon. וכשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה, u-keshe-hen chozrin te'unin bracha le-chatchila, they
do have to make a new המוציא. hamotzi. So yes, is there
an opinion that says that they do have to make a new
ברכה? bracha? Yes, that's the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if
nobody is left behind. But the חכמים Chachamim say that even if
nobody is left behind they don't have to make a new ברכה.
bracha. So that is consistent with רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, that is
consistent with the idea that as long as you had a place
where you were really having a סעודה, seudah, a שינוי מקום shinuy
makom does not require a new ברכה. bracha. Now again, that's in
a scenario where you returned, but at least it's not a contradiction
to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. It's only רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
insists on a new ברכה. bracha. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, where were we? אלא טעמא, ella ta'ima, so the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so what have you shown? דבדברים הטעונים ברכה לאחריהם במקומם,
di-bedvarim ha-te'unim bracha leachareihem bimkomam, so the reason now that you've explained
this ברייתא brayta is the חכמים Chachamim who argue on רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that say you don't need a new ברכה bracha is
that things that require ברכה bracha in that a ברכה אחרונה bracha
acharona in that same place, meaning like בענטשן, benching, that's why כשהן
יוצאין אין טעונין ברכה למפרע וכשהן חוזרין אין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה. keshe-hein
yotzin ein te'unin bracha le-mafrea u-keshe-hen chozrin ein te'unin bracha le-chatchila. That's
why when they return they don't have to make a new ברכה
bracha because they're returning to their קביעותא קמא kvi'ut kamma to where
they had originally established their meal. And the שינוי מקום shinuy makom
doesn't interrupt it. So the implication though would be אבל דברים שאין
טעונין ברכה אחריהם במקומם, aval devarim she-ein te'unin bracha leachareihem bimkomam, if
it was not something that requires עקירה... akira... It wasn't that they
like established a meal. It was something that didn't require a ברכה
bracha afterwards in the same place, like they were just סתם stam
drinking wine, or they were having meat, or whatever, it wasn't like
המוציא. Hamotzi. So if it was a scenario that was not as
to the same degree, in that case, the implication of this ברייתא
Baraita is that אפילו לרבנן, afilu le'Rabbanan, that even the Rabbis who
argue on רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would say כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה
למפריע וכשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה, kshe'hen yotzin te'unim bracha l'mafriya u'keshe'hen
chozrin te'unim bracha l'chatchila, that they would have to make a ברכה,
bracha, a bench, a ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, and they would have
to make a new ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. So, okay, what's the
problem with that? I mean what the גמרא Gemara said is again,
the scenario is the גמרא Gemara understands the ברייתא, Baraita, a group
of people are having some bread, they're having a meal, they leave,
they make a, when they come back, according to the חכמים, Chachamim,
they don't have to make a, they don't have to bench, they
don't have to make a new ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. Okay, that
is the חכמים Chachamim who argue on רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. It
doesn't matter that they left people behind. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying, it's fine. Presumably, though, the reasoning is because you set up
the scenario that they were having a meal, that they were having
like המוציא. Hamotzi. In another scenario, if they left and came back
or you know, they would have to make a new ברכה. bracha.
So the basic implication of this ברייתא Baraita is that generally שינוי
מקום shinui makom requires a new ברכה. bracha. The reason it doesn't
require a new ברכה bracha in this case according to the חכמים
Chachamim is because it was a case of עקרו akru that they
had a fixed meal, they had a סעודה, se'udah, and then they
had, they got up. But if they weren't a סעודה, se'udah, a
normal שינוי מקום shinui makom would require a ברכה. bracha. Okay, what's
the problem with that? That's what we've been saying all along, that
a normal שינוי מקום shinui makom requires a ברכה. bracha. So the
גמרא Gemara says, let's see where the גמרא Gemara is going with.
The גמרא Gemara says לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן. leima tehevay tiyuvta
d'Rabbi Yochanan. So this should be a contradiction to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said yesterday that שינוי מקום shinui
makom never requires a new ברכה. bracha. So this ברייתא Baraita seems
to be a proof against him because this ברייתא Baraita seems to
say the only reason it doesn't require a new ברכה bracha is
because it was a scenario that they were מסובין, mesubin, that they
had a fixed meal, but under other cases, changing locations would require.
So this seems to be a contradiction to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who says it never requires. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי דקא
תיובתא דרבי יוחנן ולאו מותבינן חד זימנא? u'mi de'ka tiyuvta d'Rabbi Yochanan
ve'lav motvinen chad zimna? Didn't we already contradict רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
earlier? If you remember yesterday it said תיובתא דרבי יוחנן תיובתא, tiyuvta
d'Rabbi Yochanan tiyuvta, right? We showed that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
directly contradicted that you do need a new ברכה bracha when you
switch places. Okay, yes, that's implied in this ברייתא Baraita too. Big
deal. So the גמרא Gemara says
נימא מהאי נמי תיהוי תיובתא. neima mehai nami tehevay tiyuvta. Okay, but
you know, maybe if once is good, twice is better. Right? Let's
keep it up. Can we say that this ברייתא Baraita as well
contradicts רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Now the ראשונים Rishonim say, why do
we need to, you know, to beat him up? But it's saying
because, you know, just if you have one proof against someone, although
the גמרא Gemara there did say it's an absolute contradiction, maybe somebody
will find a way out of it, maybe you'll find out it's
a corrupt text. The more proof that you can have, the more
definite your position will be that we reject רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So this רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says that you never have
to make a new ברכה. bracha. So this ברייתא Baraita again assumes
you don't make a new ברכה bracha when you, it says you
don't make a new ברכה bracha when you return, but it sounds
like only because they were having a סעודה. se'udah. If that was
not the case, they would, does this seem to be another contradiction
to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Let's read the
answer. To אמר לך רבי יוחנן, amar lecha Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan can tell you, no. הוא הדין אפילו דברים שאין טעונין
ברכה לאחריהן במקומן נמי אין צריכין לברך. hu hadin afilu devarim she'ein
te'unim bracha l'achareihem bimkomam nami ein tzrichin le'varech. You know what? The
חכמים Chachamim that say when you return you don't have to make
a new ברכה, bracha, they would say whatever you were eating, even
if you weren't eating bread, you never have to make a new
ברכה bracha just because of שינוי מקום. shinui makom. והא דקתני עקרו
רגליהם, ve'had d'katani akru ragleihem, so why did it say they uprooted
themselves? Why did it have to use that phrase which suggests that
we're talking only in a case where they're having a קביעות סעודה
kevi'at se'udah where they're really planting themselves in their place initially to
have a fixed meal? Why do we use that phrase if it's
true that you never have to make a new ברכה? bracha? להודיע
כוחו דרבי יהודה, le'hodia kocha d'Rebbe Yehuda, because then it tells you
the חידוש chiddush about how מחמיר machmir רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is.
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says that without leaving people behind you have
to make a new
ברכה. bracha. דאפילו דברים שטעונין ברכה לאחריהן במקומן, d'afilu devarim she'te'unim bracha
l'achareihem bimkomam, even a case where you do have to, it is
like a meal, where you would have to make benching in that
place, where you had bread, where you were קובע סעודה. kove'a se'udah.
Even in those
scenarios, the only way רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda gets you out of
it is דהניחו מקצת חבריהם, d'hinichu miktzat chaveireihem, only when some people
were left behind. אבל לא הניחו מקצת חבריהם, aval lo hinichu miktzat
chaveireihem, when people weren't left behind, כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפריע וכשהן
חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה. kshe'hen yotzin te'unim bracha l'mafriya u'keshe'hen chozrin te'unim
bracha l'chatchila. In that case, you would always have to make a
new ברכה. bracha. So again, to repeat the scenarios we've got, okay?
I think this is getting a little confusing.
Oh look, we have comics! So, so this
is
what we've got. What?
Yes.
So anyway, so of course so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, do
you have to make a new ברכה bracha when you have שינוי
מקום? shinui makom? He says never. Okay? And here you have רב
הונא Rav Huna and רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So they say, they
say yes, you do have to make a new ברכה, bracha, but
רב ששת Rav Sheshet says always, and רב הונא Rav Huna says
only... If not סעודה, seuda, המוציא, Hamotzi, okay, המוציא Hamotzi or מזונות.
Mezonos. But if it was המוציא Hamotzi or מזונות, Mezonos, then you
do, then you do not have to make a new ברכה. bracha.
Okay, those are the different range of opinions. We had already had
a ברייתא braitah we said that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we had
contradicted him. Okay, now we have this case, right, which is the
people that you have the things that you have the bread. Here's
all these people sitting and eating. Okay. Okay, there's their loaf of
bread. Alright, and they have to, they get up and they go
to חתן chassan and כלה, kallah, right? So that's the case, that's
the ברייתא braitah that we have. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says,
so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that normally if they didn't leave
people behind, right, no one left behind. Who's that no one left
behind? No child left behind. But no one is left behind, so
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you have to make a ברכה bracha
and the חכמים Chachamim say you don't.
Okay, you don't. Okay, so we're assuming that we're talking that it
was a סעודה. seuda. So how does this work? So basically you
see look, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you do make a ברכה.
bracha. That's basically similar to רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב ששת Rav
Sheshet says you always make, you always make a new ברכה. bracha.
חכמים Chachamim say you don't, but that works with רב הונא Rav
Huna because here you're having a סעודה. seuda. So if you're having
a סעודה, seuda, so you do not have to, right? רב הונא
Rav Huna says if you have a סעודה, seuda, then no. Okay,
so that's how we sort of fixed out the ברייתא. braitah. That
look, the חכמים Chachamim disagree with רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The חכמים
Chachamim say you don't need it, it's because you're having a סעודה.
seuda. So that's consistent with רב הונא Rav Huna who says that
when you're having a סעודה seuda you don't have to make a
new ברכה. bracha. So גמרא Gemara says okay, but everybody basically here
seems to say that if you weren't having a סעודה, seuda, if
it wasn't a special case, then presumably everybody would say you have
to make a new
ברכה. bracha. Presumably the only reason חכמים Chachamim are saying is don't
make a new ברכה bracha is because the case of having a
סעודה. seuda. So it proves against רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that everybody
basically says that if it weren't for this סעודה, seuda, you would
have to make a new ברכה. bracha. And the גמרא's Gemara answer
is no, the חכמים Chachamim might say you never. If רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is to tell you is that the חכמים Chachamim would
say you never have to make, even if it's no bread. Why
did we mention the bread? To tell you even with the bread,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is always going to require a new ברכה.
bracha. I don't know if that helped at all. But anyway. Okay,
yes.
So people you leave behind, they don't have to actually be eating,
right? They can just be sitting there? Presumably. But you know, if
they're eating let's say, then other people join in and leave people,
who knows?
Let's keep on
reading.
תניא כוותיה, tanya kevasi, yeah. I just find it peculiar that you
have a קולא kullah position so to speak, but you say you
do not have to make a ברכה bracha למפרע l'mafrea or לכתחילה
l'chatichila when it's the so to speak more serious requirement of saying
ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon. Yes, as opposed to having a snack which
requires you to say ברכות. brachos. You've got sort of a what
to my mind is more of a it's ironic that, right, right,
that the bread case has a קולא kullah position.
Right, but that's I think the logic is look, and you I
also think it's ironic because you would say that if it's something
about a fixed place, then a different place is more obviously something
different, it's more breaking with that fixed place. But the argument seems
to be that when you're having bread and when you're having a
סעודה, seuda, that somehow defines everything in terms of it, so it
makes everything, it's more linked to that original eating and it's not
seen in terms of קולא kullah or
חומרא.
chumrah. Yes, it's also where
היסח הדעת, hesach hadas, if you're having
coffee and you leave, well the הלכה halakha is more מחמיר. machmir.
You have to say the ברכה bracha even if it's not, you
don't have to return necessarily,
it's more מחמיר.
machmir. Whereas it's a קולא kullah position with the דברים הטעונים ברכה
במקומם. devarim hatuunim berachah bimkomam. Right. Also between courses? That's היסח הדעת.
hesach hadas. Right. But you don't necessarily have היסח הדעת hesach hadas
with coffee, but you're not necessarily... right, right, I do think that
exactly ties in, meaning psychologically as well because the סעודה seuda makes
you always more connected to that. Exactly. Okay, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara says that yes, we have this case of a סעודה
seuda which fits that the
חכמים Chachamim say you don't make a new ברכה. bracha. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you do. That so that in a way falls
out to the debate of רב הונא Rav Huna and רב ששת
Rav Sheshet with a סעודה. seuda. Can you infer from this that
without a סעודה seuda everybody says you make a new ברכה? bracha?
No, maybe we said a סעודה seuda to tell you how far
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda goes. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda always, even with
a סעודה. seuda. Maybe the חכמים, Chachamim,
who knows, maybe they would be like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Okay.
We end this by saying תניא כוותיה tanya kevasi דרב חסדא. d'Rav
Chisda. We taught like רב חסדא: Rav Chisda: חברים שהיו מסובין לשתות
יין ועקרו רגליהם וחזרו, chaveirim she'hayu mesubin lishos yayin ve'akeru ragleihem ve'chazaru,
exactly this case, אין צריכים לברך. ein tzrichim levarech. So you do
not have to make a ברכה. bracha. It says it without qualification,
without the רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now again, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
might say that's always true. But at least רב חסדא Rav Chisda
would emphasize the עקרו רגליהם. akru ragleihem. It's true because they were
קובע סעודה kovea seuda and when they return, therefore they do not
have to. There's a big debate in the ראשונים rishonim how do
we פסקן. pasken. Although the גמרא Gemara seems to be weighing in
the end towards רב הונא, Rav Huna, the רי"ף Rif פסקנס paskens
like רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So there's a whole debate whether in
the end we certainly don't פסקן pasken like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
But some ראשונים rishonim say always
שינוי מקום. shinnui makom. I'm not going to talk about all the
practical implications of that. Sorry, Michael. Okay, I want to do point
do point out one thing about this עקרו רגליהם לילך, akra ragleihem
leileich, or two things about עקרו רגליהם לילך. akra ragleihem leileich. Why
does it mention all of these מצוות, mitzvos, בית הכנסת Beis Haknesses
and חתן וכלה? Chosson Vekallah? So the בעל המאור Ba'al HaMa'or and
the ראב"ד Ra'avad both say that it's telling you that you need
that that normally you shouldn't be interrupting your meal, meaning not just
out of an etiquette thing, but presumably because of these issues about
ברכות brachos and so on, you know, that if it was a
דבר רשות, dvar reshus, then you you know then finish your meal
and בענטש bentch before you go off to doing these types of
things rather than interrupting it. You interrupt, you might not come back,
it'll be ברכה bracha questions, you'll forget to make the ברכה אחרונה.
bracha achrona. But we allow you to do it לכתחילה lechatchila when
it's this דבר מצווה. dvar mitzvah. That's what the ראב"ד Ra'avad בעל
המאור Ba'al HaMa'or says, not in the גמרא, Gemara, but that's what
they say. But there's another interesting question about this idea לילך לבית
הכנסת. leileich leBeis Haknesses. Take a look at תוספות Tosfos and this
does come up sometimes. עקרו רגליהם לילך לבית הכנסת. akra ragleihem leileich
leBeis Haknesses. תוספות Tosfos says מכאן משמע שאם שכח להתפלל ונזכר באמצע
סעודה, mikan mashma she'im shachach lehispalel venizkar be'emtza seudah, never happens to
me, ויתפלל שאין צריך ברכה אפילו לכתחילה. ve'yispaleil she'ein tzarich bracha afilu
lechatchila. There you are, you're eating and all of a sudden you
remember, oh my God, I didn't דאווען daven מנחה Mincha and it's
going to be שקיעה shkia in five minutes. Okay, so you get
up and you דאווען daven מנחה Mincha at home. You have to
now, is that like עקרו רגליהם, akra ragleihem, right, and go to
the בית הכנסת? Beis Haknesses? And now would you have to make
a, assuming we פסקן pasken like רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, let's say
you weren't having bread, would that be considered an interruption and you
would have to make a new ברכה? bracha? So תוספות Tosfos says
it says that שאין צריך ברכה אפילו לכתחילה. she'ein tzarich bracha afilu
lechatchila. Why? Because it says עקרו רגליהם לילך לבית הכנסת, akra ragleihem
leileich leBeis Haknesses, that there was a שינוי מקום shinui makom involved,
but just the act of דאווענינג davening itself would not be an
interruption. Okay, and then he quotes another גמרא Gemara that might contradict
him and he says that גמרא Gemara is not a proof. So
תוספות Tosfos actually says that if you have to interrupt a meal
and דאווען, daven, not go to שול shul to דאווען, daven, but
דאווען daven in the place, the act of דאווענינג davening is not
a הפסק. hefsek. It's only because you were עוקר oker the מקום,
makom, that created the issue of שינוי מקום. shinui makom. Okay, so
I thought I'd raise that because that is something that at least
that I know does come up from time to time.
Back in those days, if they had to go to the bathroom
and you know and they had to go do a whole thing?
Right, that's the interesting point. You know again, I assume that that
raises a good question about the context of שינוי מקום shinui makom
because you could argue the other point as well. שינוי מקום shinui
makom in itself, you know maybe that gets to sort of the
issue about intention. שינוי מקום shinui makom in itself when it constitutes
a new activity, when the שינוי מקום shinui makom constitutes a continuation
of the same activity, or going to the bathroom like a necessary
part of you know of things that come up right during the
meal. You know, we gave the scenario you're at a wedding in
a שמאָרג smorg and you're going to different places and you go
to the terrace and you walk outdoors. Right, so I think that's
a good question, right, which is that how does other things such
as context and intention, you know, define מקום makom or define... Yes,
absolutely, absolutely, yes. So I think you're absolutely correct about that, yeah.
And the constant term חברים, chaveirim, in technical terms חברים? chaveirim?
I think it's anybody, yeah. I don't think that it's, yeah, I
don't get any sense that it's the classic חבר. chaver. בני מסובין?
b'nei mesubin? Yeah, it's a good question. I don't know. I mean,
it just it gives, you know, you could also say why did
it say that they went because of חתן וכלה chosson vekallah if
you ignore the ראב"ד? Ra'avad? I think it's trying to just create
a realistic scenario, but I don't I'd not treat חברים chaveirim as
too technical.
The בני חבורה, b'nei chaburah, בני חברים, b'nei chaveirim, so I think
it was...
Okay, so let's now we'd hear about בני חבורה. b'nei chaburah. Let's
take a look at that case. תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: בני חבורה...
b'nei chaburah... but you know Rivka you're correct in reminding us that
the word חבורה chaburah and חברים chaveirim can definitely have a technical
sense about these people, group of people that were like this elite
group that would only eat their you know their חולין בטהרה chullin
b'tahara and there would be a whole ques... you know be very
careful about not letting outsiders eat together with them. So when we
are talking a lot about eating, so it does raise an interesting
question, you know and in the and in the Tannaitic you know
literature, the issues of the חבורה chaburah are much more of a
concern than they are later like in the גמרא. Gemara. So in
all of these ברייתות baraitas I hadn't thought about that, but all
these ברייתות baraitas that refer to חברים chaveirim and בני חבורה, b'nei
chaburah, are they being used somewhat like you know sort of
you know imprecisely to refer to just some a similar phenomenon of
people of a group or are they being technical? I wouldn't know
why they would have to be technical, but it's important to remember
that model of חבורה chaburah that it exists.
That's nice because the intentionality of eating together in טהרה tahara and
טומאה tumah gets transposed perhaps at a certain point into the intentionality
of saying ברכות.
brachos. Oh, that's an interesting idea, using that model and now talking
about how it the reality is created through ברכות, brachos, that certain
sense of cohesion and intentionality. That's a very nice idea.
And those people when they went from one place to another always
had to be thinking about טומאה, tumah, טהרה.
tahara. Yes, שינוי מקום shinui makom maybe is a bigger issue. That's
a good point too. Who knows? You could write, that sounds like
a paper right there. The real... The whole base of שינוי מקום
shinui makom is rooted in these concerns of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah.
Who knows? תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: בני חבורה שהיו מסובין, bnei chaburah
shehayu mesubbin, so people of a group or חבורה chaburah that were
reclining and eating, וקדש עליהם היום v'kadesh aleihem hayom and then it
became the day got sanctified, which meant it was Friday and it
became שבת. Shabbos. מביאים לו כוס של יין, mevi'im lo kos shel
yayin, so this is going to be the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi of do you interrupt? But now we're
not just talking about interrupting, but how you handle the possible interruption
in terms of ברכות. brachot. So מביאים לו כוס של יין ואומר
עליו קדושת היום והשני אומר עליו ברכת המזון, mevi'im lo kos shel
yayin v'omer alav kedushat hayom v'hasheni omer alav birkat hamazon, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei rabbi yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you have
to interrupt your meal. You stop eating now, and you have to
say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and קידוש. kiddush. And the second, the
second cup. Okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says something a little
bit surprising. You would have thought that first you do ברכת המזון,
birkat hamazon, you finish up the day, then you do קידוש. kiddush.
Now there is a question of the גירסא girsa of this ברייתא.
braita. Some גירסאות girsaot have that with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, first
you do ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, then you do קידוש. kiddush. Our
גירסא girsa is first you do קידוש, kiddush, then you do
ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. What is the reason for that order? So
תוספות tosafot says the reason would be
because you can't, if you make ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, again they're
doing it they're talking about taking a cup of wine, they're assuming
that ברכת המזון birkat hamazon is על הכוס. al hakos. Well if
you make ברכת המזון על הכוס birkat hamazon al hakos and it
now became dark and it became Friday night and you're making ברכת
המזון birkat hamazon from your Friday חולין chullin על הכוס, al hakos,
what problem are you going to have when you're done with ברכת
המזון? birkat hamazon? How can you drink from the כוס, kos, it's
already Friday night and I can't drink from the כוס kos without
making קידוש. kiddush. So therefore you have to make קידוש kiddush first,
although it's ironic, and then wrap up the previous meal so you
can drink from the כוס kos of ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. That's
what?
Right, you want
to incorporate this as your step? No, no. This is רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wants you to be done with
your Friday meal and start your שבת Shabbos meal, but because you
have to do ברכת המזון על הכוס, birkat hamazon al hakos, according
to תוספות tosafot you have to do קידוש kiddush first. The בעל
המאור, ba'al hama'or, somebody else says I think I forget, that
no, that since the
thing that forced you to say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon was the
קידוש, kiddush, was the new day, you start with that. That was
in a sense the interruption or the pause of the ברכת המזון
birkat hamazon and it's followed by the ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. But
that's a stranger idea. תוספות tosafot basically says it's just a technical
need of being able to say ברכת המזון על הכוס. birkat hamazon
al hakos. Now of course it's strange because the whole idea for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was to create an interruption. So תוספות tosafot
says that's why before you do the קידוש, kiddush, you'll be מסלק
את השולחן. mesalek et hashulchan. That was discussed before, right, about the
סילוק השולחן. siluk hashulchan. Fine, you remove the table, that created the
division, that created the break. But now in terms of the ברכות,
brachot, we have to for technical reasons do קידוש kiddush first. That's
the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר אוכל והולך
עד שתחשך. rabbi yossi omer ochel v'holech ad shetechshach. Here's the רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi we know. Keep on eating until it gets dark.
Now what do you do when you're done eating according to רבי
יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? Okay, you also have to בענטש bench and now
make קידוש. kiddush. What order do you do? So גמרו, gamru,
you finished your meal, כוס ראשון מברך עליו ברכת המזון והשני אומר
עליו קדושת היום. kos rishon mevarech alav birkat hamazon v'hasheni omer alav
kedushat hayom. Now it's very the order makes sense, right? You do
ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, you wrap it up and then you do
קדושת היום. kedushat hayom. Of course according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
you know, it's not exactly clear why he doesn't have רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda's concern, because one does wonder, right, although I was allowed
to continue eating my meal after it got dark, that's because it
was a continuation of the previous meal. It was still considered a
weekday meal. Now that I'm בענטשינג benching and I'm saying it על
הכוס, al hakos, right, after now that I'm done with my meal,
maybe I should have the same concern that I can't eat until
I make קידוש. kiddush. So it is a little bit interesting, right,
that רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, is that clear? Meaning what the reality
for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi when you're done with your meal is
not clear why it is so different than the reality for רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. You're done with your meal, you have to do
ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, you have to make קידוש, kiddush, maybe even
though רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi let me eat when it got dark,
that was when it was part of the meal. Now that I've
בענטשד, benched, maybe I should have to do קידוש kiddush before I
can drink the wine of ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. But apparently not,
and apparently again maybe still, you know, we already allowed you to
be eating, so even the wine of the ברכת המזון birkat hamazon
will maybe be considered a continuation of that and he lets you
do the normal order. You do ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and then
you do קידוש. kiddush. Now everybody points out this isn't the way,
this isn't relevant for us because we פוסקים poskim פורס מפה ומקדש.
pores mappah u'mekadesh. I wanted to use this opportunity before we continue
the גמרא gemara though, because I was reminding myself of the הלכות
halachot about the פורס מפה ומקדש. pores mappah u'mekadesh. So it's interesting,
everybody agrees if you have the פורס מפה ומקדש, pores mappah u'mekadesh,
we said this could happen on פורים Purim let's say, I mean
it could happen other times, it could happen let's say פורים Purim
and you're having your meal and you're having wine, and then you
have to do פורס מפה ומקדש. pores mappah u'mekadesh. What do you
do in terms of בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen and in
terms of המוציא? hamotzi? So everybody agrees you do not make a
new בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagafen. It's very strange. You would
actually make קידוש kiddush without בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagafen. You'll
start קידוש, kiddush, you would say the thing before, or you just
start, you know, with the ברכה bracha after בורא פרי הגפן, borei
pri hagafen, אשר קדשנו במצותיו ורצה בנו, asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav v'ratza banu,
right, so אשר קדשנו. asher kidshanu. Etcetera. So imagine making the קידוש
Kiddush without the בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, just jumping right
in. Because בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen is not technically a
ברכה Beracha of the קידוש, Kiddush, it's incorporated into the קידוש Kiddush
because you need it in order to make קידוש על היין Kiddush
al hayayin and you're going to need it to drink the wine.
But since you've already been drinking wine, if it's a פורים סעודה
Purim Seuda or סתם stam for you know if you've been drinking
wine, you the and this is this is immediately following without interruption
it doesn't need a new בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. So
some people say that בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen is part
of קידוש. Kiddush. Yeah, I know, it is true. If you have
to make it for somebody else, so you'd have to say when
it's needed it becomes part of קידוש. Kiddush. But when it's but
if it's not needed it's not needed, it's true. But that is
but yes, you do have both of those הלכות Halachot that when
you do have to make it you can make it for somebody
and it's not just a ברכת הנהנין. Birkat HaNehenin. But if it's
but if it's not needed at all, you actually would make and
this is this is הלכה, Halacha, you make קידוש Kiddush without בורא
פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. Now, do you make המוציא? Hamotzi? Do
you say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen and then do you
just take off the thing and jump into the bread? Or do
you have to
make now a new
המוציא? Hamotzi? So here there's a big debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim.
Because some say no, the act of קידוש, Kiddush, right, קידוש Kiddush
didn't need בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, you were still in
the middle of eating and you could drink the wine, but the
act of קידוש, Kiddush, now that you now that you have made
the קידוש, Kiddush, that now says that this is a new meal.
As a new meal, sort of like the שינוי מקום, shinui makom,
even though you're sitting at the table and all the food is
there, as a new meal it needs a new המוציא. Hamotzi. And
others disagree. If it yes it has become a שבת Shabbos meal
but without an interruption and it doesn't need a new המוציא. Hamotzi.
So the you know the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch brings down both
opinions, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah says ספק ברכות להקל, Safek Berachos
L'Hakel, you don't make המוציא. Hamotzi. So it would be fascinating in
this case, you would actually go ahead and make קידוש Kiddush without
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen and then have the לחם משנה
Lechem Mishneh and uncover the לחם משנה Lechem Mishneh and eat them
without a המוציא. Hamotzi. So it'd be a fun thing to do
on a Friday פורים Purim just in order to have that like
experience of living that הלכה. Halacha.
Yeah. I've not been to one, but this שול shul when פורים
Purim falls out on Friday does have late afternoon סעודות. seudot.
Ah, so I wonder yeah if you know what they I assume
they do that they do that directly.
Yeah yeah, they have the whole issue of דאווענינג davening and stuff
like that, but but you so you wouldn't have to make בורא
פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, you're saying only because presumably you would
I think...
Yeah, because for a פורים סעודה Purim Seuda I assume you've been
drinking wine.
Yeah, what if you've been drinking alcohol, not wine?
Well, that's a problem because פורים סעודה Purim Seuda requires wine. I
mean the definition of the whole issue of חייב לבסומי chiyav livsumei
and משתה Mishteh and so on. Okay, anyway let's go on. So
now we have this debate, so now we've known the debate of
רב יהודה Reb Yehuda and רב יוסי, Reb Yosi, but now we're
also seeing that they're debating or they're discussing what to do with
the ברכות. Berachot. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, why is it that you
need Michael's question, two כוסות? kosot? ונימרינהו לתרוייהו אחדא כסא, V'nimreinhu letarvaihu
achada kasa, say both ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and קידוש Kiddush on
the same כוס. kos. Now תוספות Tosafot says this is only according
to רב יוסי, Reb Yosi, even though both רב יוסי Reb Yosi
and רב יהודה Reb Yehuda have two ברכות. Berachot. Because according to
רב יהודה, Reb Yehuda, the whole point is is that the ברכת
המזון Birkat Hamazon was to end the previous thing and the קידוש
Kiddush was to start the new thing and the whole idea was
to separate them, so there's no way you're going to use one
כוס kos to do them both, the whole point is to separate
them. Okay, but according to רב יוסי, Reb Yosi, he says actually
according to רב יוסי Reb Yosi you need to combine them. Why?
Because remember תוספות Tosafot asks the question, according to רב יוסי, Reb
Yosi, how do you have קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bemakom Seuda if
you're done with all your eating and then you're making קידוש? Kiddush?
And how do you have what meal is your first סעודת שבת
Seudat Shabbos if presumably you're not eating a new meal now that
you're done with all your eating? So he says according to רב
יוסי Reb Yosi once you've made קידוש Kiddush after the סעודה, Seuda,
that is a that defines it as קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bemakom
Seuda and that retroactively also defines what you've been eating as סעודת
שבת. Seudat Shabbos. Okay, that's תוספות's Tosafot חידוש chiddush that according to
רב יוסי Reb Yosi his explanation, the קידוש Kiddush becomes after and
works together with the סעודה, Seuda, which might also explain why רב
יוסי Reb Yosi allows you to do ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon first.
Because it's all one thing, it's not these two separated things like
תוספות. Tosafot. So if that's true, make ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and
קידוש Kiddush with the same כוס. kos. The whole point is that
you're incorporating the קידוש Kiddush afterwards into the meal. So use the
same כוס. kos. So why not use the same כוס? kos? So
אמר רב הונא אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav Sheshet,
אין אומרים שתי קדושות על כוס אחד. ein omrim shtei kedushot al
kos echad. רב הונא Rav Huna and רב ששת Rav Sheshet were
arguing in the דף daf before, now they're both saying and they
agree. אמר רב הונא אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav
Sheshet, he said in the name of רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, אין
אומרים שתי קדושות על כוס אחד. ein omrim shtei kedushot al kos
echad. You don't do two sanctifications, obviously one is a ברכת המזון,
Birkat Hamazon, but on the same כוס.
kos. Okay, so you have to have two כוסות kosot under a
חופה? chuppah?
We're I'll talk about that in a minute. I'll talk about that
in a minute. One minute. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why not? אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak לפי שאין עושין
מצות חבילות חבילות. lefi she'ein osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos. You don't bundle
up your מצות. mitzvot. The way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is
you don't want it to seem like it's a burden, like oh
good let's you know let's reuse this and do double duty with
this כוס. kos. Don't use your לולב Lulav to burn the חמץ?
Chametz? Yeah, it's a question, but you know each one deserves right
because
that's
once one מצוה mitzvah was done do another מצוה mitzvah with it.
Yeah, it's a good point, I mean you are correct, that's slightly
you know, but but here I would reframe it as the whole
idea of קידוש על הכוס Kiddush al hakos and ברכת המזון על
הכוס... Birkat Hamazon al hakos... If you say something על הכוס, al
hakos, it gives weight and significance to this ritual act. I mean,
just think about it, by the way, I don't know if people
are aware, but according to the גמרא, Gemara, you do not say
שבע ברכות על הכוס, Sheva Brachot al hakos, you do not say
ברכת אירוסין על הכוס, Birkat Erusin al hakos, you do not do
ברכת מילה על הכוס. Birkat Milah al hakos. All of that act
came later. And I think that we, if we were not to
do those things על הכוס, al hakos, they would not have the
same religious impact. Doing it על הכוס al hakos gives a lot
of weight and makes it into a ritual, gives it a lot
of—what? Looks religious?
Exactly,
it gives it this significance.
So I would argue this idea in general, אין עושין מצוות חבילות
חבילות, Ein Osin Mitzvot Chavilot Chavilot, comes up in other contexts, but
here in particular, you want to give weight to this ברכה. Bracha.
You don't want to reuse some other כוס Kos which actually anyway,
you know, it's like also defines it not in its own terms.
So this was a כוס ברכת המזון Kos Birkat Hamazon you used
for this. So is this a קידוש Kiddush or is this a
ברכת המזון? Birkat Hamazon? So I think particularly in the context of
קידוש, Kiddush, where the whole idea is that the כוס Kos is
giving weight and the כוס Kos is connected to the identity, you
don't want to double up and muddy the waters. Okay, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara answer. Let's continue a little bit and then I'll
talk about the חופה Chuppah question. ולא, Velo, do you not do
that? והתניא, Vehatanya, but it was taught in a ברייתא: Braisa: הנכנס
לביתו במוצאי שבת, Hanichnas lebeito bemotzei Shabbat, one who enters his house
on מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbat, מברך על היין ועל המאור ועל הבשמים,
mevarech al hayayin veal hamaor veal habesamim, he blesses on the יין,
Yayin, on the מאור, Meor, and on the בשמים. Besamim. You came
home on מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbat, so this is הבדלה, Havdalah, right?
יין, Yayin, מאור, Meor, בשמים. Besamim. We do יין, Yayin, בשמים, Besamim,
מאור. Meor. We'll talk about that order later. ואחר כך אומר הבדלה,
Veachar kach omer Havdalah, okay, so that's your normal הבדלה Havdalah על
הכוס. al hakos. ואם אין לו אלא כוס אחד, Veim ein lo
ela kos echad, now let's say you only have one כוס Kos
of יין Yayin and you need it for ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
because you've also been eating. So what do you do? ואם אין
לו אלא כוס אחד, Veim ein lo ela kos echad, מניחו לאחר
המזון. mianicho leachar hamazon. So the כוס Kos you were going to
use for ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, let's say for your שלוש סעודות,
Shalosh Seudot, so you leave it till after you're done eating.
What's the case? You said you came to your house.
So that's a good question, right? So could be you came to
your house, I'll discuss that, but for now we're assuming we're talking
about a different scenario. Not you came home from שול, Shul, but
you were at home, you were eating, you were having שלוש סעודות,
Shalosh Seudot, and you only have one כוס Kos of יין. Yayin.
Do you use it for בענטשין benching or do you use it
for הבדלה? Havdalah? What are you going to do?
The issue is the physical cup or the quantity?
No, no, no, the amount of יין. Yayin. כוס אחד Kos echad
is a way of saying one כוס's Kos worth of יין. Yayin.
Okay, so what do you do? One minute. So what do you
do? מניחו לאחר המזון, mianicho leachar hamazon, you use it for בענטשין
benching and you set it aside, ומשלשלן כולן לאחריו, umeshalshalan kulan leacharav,
and you string them all together afterwards. משלשל Meshalshal is the word
like a שלשלת, shalshelet, like a chain. Right, you string all,
you know, you daisy-chain all of the ברכות Brachot on it. So
basically, you see what you're doing here is you're saying ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon and הבדלה Havdalah all on the same כוס. Kos. So
you see you can bundle up? גמרא Gemara says, אין לו שאני.
Ein lo shani. No, if you don't have, if you only have
one כוס, Kos, we'll give you a little latitude. But when you
have two כוסות, kosot, you should use separate כוסות. kosot. That's where
you only had one. Now Michael asks a question. Michael says why
do we switch scenarios? We talk about coming home and then we
talk about you're sitting and you're eating and you need a כוס
Kos for ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. I mean, if you came home
after שול, Shul, don't eat until you make הבדלה. Havdalah. So some
say, אה"נ, in hami, we're talking about a different scenario. תוספות Tosafot
says no, because here's the thing. You only have one כוס. Kos.
You came home from שול. Shul. Now we know you're not allowed
to eat before הבדלה, Havdalah, but you're planning tonight to have your
סעודה, Seudah, and if you're poor—you know, if a guy only has
one כוס Kos of יין, Yayin, he's probably pretty poor—so the main
part of your meal is going to be your bread. Okay, so
you're already planning in advance and you're saying to yourself, if I
go ahead and make הבדלה Havdalah now על הכוס, al hakos, I'm
not going to have a כוס יין Kos yayin for when I
later want to eat my sandwich. So we will allow you to,
תוספות, Tosafot, to have your meal before הבדלה, Havdalah, even though you're
not allowed to normally eat before הבדלה, Havdalah, in order to enable
you to do a ברכת המזון על הכוס Birkat Hamazon al hakos
and to wrap it up with הבדלה Havdalah because you only have
one כוס Kos of יין. Yayin. Which is pretty amazing, like my
first response reading that תוספות, Tosafot, so don't have bread, have something
else. Okay, but that wasn't so much of an option, especially if
you were poor. But my second point is, you know, so don't
make ברכת המזון על הכוס. Birkat Hamazon al hakos. Okay, since when
do we normally have ברכת המזון על הכוס? Birkat Hamazon al hakos?
Maybe if you have ten people and you happen to have some
יין Yayin around, but clearly in the גמרא, Gemara, you see from
all the cases we're reading, what do you—you know, that the, you
know, everybody says what do you do when you're מפסיק, mafsik, you
make ברכת המזון על הכוס Birkat Hamazon al hakos and you make
this על הכוס. al hakos. The assumption is you're always making ברכת
המזון על הכוס, Birkat Hamazon al hakos, presumably even a יחיד, yachid,
even by yourself. The גמרא Gemara like takes that completely for granted.
So in order to allow you to have your sandwich and to
do ברכת המזון על הכוס, Birkat Hamazon al hakos, תוספות Tosafot says
we'll allow you to eat before הבדלה. Havdalah.
So I was just like including this שול, Shul, when they have
the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon for שלוש סעודות, Shalosh Seudot, they do
it על הכוס al hakos and then they use the same כוס
Kos for הבדלה Havdalah even when there's gallons of grape juice around.
Right, so there is—I mean, and that which is against the idea
of אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות. Ein Osin Mitzvot Chavilot Chavilot. Yeah,
that idea definitely is brought down and as Michael says, once you
did one
מצוה, Mitzvah, you
know, with it... That really becomes like an idea to use the
same כוס Kos for doing both.
Okay, that's different. There are other גמרות Gemorot and more in ברכות
Berakhot that talk about the different practices about ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
on a כוס, Kos, but certainly the גמרא Gemara assumes we're always
doing it.
Now, I want to read to the two dots and then I
want also discuss the case of the חופה. Chuppah. Says the גמרא
Gemara that we're still saying now you don't use the same כוס
Kos for two, although Charlie correctly reminds us that we often דווקא
Davka do that in a case of שלוש סעודות Shalosh Seudot and
הבדלה. Havdalah. Now, והאי יום טוב, Ve-hai Yom Tov, but here's another
question. יום טוב שחל להיות אחר שבת. Yom Tov she-chal lihyos achar
Shabbos.
If יום טוב Yom Tov comes after שבת, Shabbat, right, so we
had יום טוב Yom Tov before שבת Shabbat this holiday season, but
if יום טוב Yom Tov came after שבת, Shabbat, then you're going
to make a הבדלה Havdalah and קידוש Kiddush at the same time
because you only make הבדלה Havdalah from a יום טוב Yom Tov
שבת Shabbat juxtaposition when יום טוב Yom Tov follows שבת Shabbat because
יום טוב Yom Tov is a lesser קדושה. Kedushah. And הבדלה Havdalah
is always from a higher קדושה Kedushah to a non-קדושה Kedushah or
lesser קדושה. Kedushah. So you'll never make it from יום טוב Yom
Tov into שבת, Shabbat, but you'll make it from שבת Shabbat into
יום טוב. Yom Tov So שבת Shabbat and then יום טוב, Yom
Tov. יום טוב Yom Tov, is Sunday, you'll make הבדלה, Havdalah, but
you'll also have to make קידוש Kiddush for יום טוב. Yom Tov
So how are you going to like incorporate or what order are
you going to do these things? So let's take a look. ויום
טוב שחל להיות אחר שבת. Ve-Yom Tov She-chal Lihyot Achar Shabbat. יום
טוב Yom Tov. comes after שבת. Shabbat. ודאי אית ליה, Vedai It
Lei, obviously in that case you have two cups of wine. Now
why is it obvious you have two cups of wine? תוספות Tosafot
says, well look, it's one thing to say by הבדלה Havdalah time
you've had you know you've really enjoyed your שבת Shabbat and you're
left to your last cup of wine. This actually happens, you know,
sometimes at הבדלה Havdalah and we have no wine or grape juice
left by the end of שבת Shabbat just anyway. But at the
beginning, you know, it's יום טוב, Yom Tov anyway יום טוב Yom
Tov, is a time where it's supposed to be, you know, חג
שמח Chag Sameach and you have whatever, presumably it's the beginning of
a יום טוב, Yom Tov you're going to have your wine, store
will still be good, so you know, your stock. So therefore presumably
you have two cups of wine. ואמר רב, Ve-amar Rav, and רב
Rav says יקנה. Yakneh. So you do יין, קידוש, נר, הבדלה. yayin
kiddush ner havdalah, The order you do is יין Yayin, and קידוש,
Kiddush, קידוש Kiddush, comes first and הבדלה Havdalah. afterwards. Again that's ironic,
it's sort of like קידוש Kiddush before ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon when
do you first want to end the previous one and start the
new one? So we'll talk about that in a minute. But the
point though being is you use the same כוס Kos for קידוש
Kiddush as you do for הבדלה. Havdalah So don't you see you
use one כוס Kos for two things, for two separate ברכות? Berakhot?
So אמרי מדלא אמר זמן. Amri Midla Amar Zman. Let's figure out
what scenario we're talking about. Why did רב Rav not talk about
זמן, Zman, שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, right? You say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu when you say
קידוש. Kiddush So what is the only קידוש Kiddush. of יום טוב
Yom Tov, you make without a שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu? The only time you
make קידוש Kiddush on יום טוב Yom Tov without a שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu?
שביעי של
פסח,
Shevi'i Shel
Pesach, right? שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is a חג בפני עצמו, Chag
Bifnei Atzmo, so you make שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, right? You make a שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu on for in חוץ לארץ Chutz La-aretz on both days of
יום טוב Yom Tov beginning and end because of the ספיקא דיומא.
Sfeika De-yoma. So the only time you don't is שביעי של פסח,
Shevi'i Shel Pesach, that's seen as a continuation. So why didn't he
mention זמן? Zman? מכלל דבשביעי של פסח עסקינן. Miklal Debeshevi'i Shel Pesach
Iskinan. We're talking about שביעי של פסח. Shevi'i Shel Pesach. So in
that case the end of פסח, Pesach, דכל מאי דהוה ליה אכליה,
Dekol Mai Dehava Lei Achlei, ולית ליה. Veleit Lei.
So that's the case, it's the end of פסח, Pesach, yeah you're
done with you've eaten up all of your
פסחדיקע Pesach-dikke products, you've drank all your wine, yeah that's also a
scenario of having only one cup of wine. So which is a
pretty weak answer. Okay, but anyway but the גמרא Gemara says because
nevertheless like presumably רב Rav is giving you a general ruling. So
the גמרא Gemara says fine, I'll give you another case. יום טוב
ראשון דאית ליה. Yom Tov Rishon De-it Lei. How about a first
day of יום טוב? Yom Tov Or even שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeret?
A day that you're where you obviously that day you'll have, you
know, it's a new יום טוב, Yom Tov? you're going to have
a lot of wine. ואמר אביי, Ve-amar Abaye, and there we also
see they're discussing the order יקזנ"ה. Yakzneh. ורב אמר יקנה"ז. Ve-Rav Amar
Yaknehaz. Okay,
this is going to be fun fun. So אביי Abaye says when
you have to do a הבדלה Havdalah. and קידוש Kiddush and a
שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, right, it's anything other than שביעי של פסח, Shevi'i Shel
Pesach, in that case you do ייין קידוש זמן Yayin Kiddush Zman
which is the classic קידוש. Kiddush You do the whole קידוש Kiddush.
and then you do the הבדלה נר הבדלה. Havdalah Ner Havdalah. Why
there's no בשמים Besamim I'll talk about in a minute. So אביי
Abaye again makes a lot of sense, at least I mean we
would want הבדלה Havdalah first, but anyway, do the full קידוש Kiddush
and then do the הבדלה. Havdalah ורב אמר יקנה"ז, Ve-Rav Amar Yaknehaz,
which is actually how we rule. ייין קידוש נר הבדלה Yayin Kiddush
Ner Havdalah and you do שהחיינו Shehecheyanu at the very end, which
is strange. But regardless what you see is that at the beginning
of יום טוב Yom Tov, you're saying שהחיינו Shehecheyanu presumably you have
two cups of wine and we're still incorporating it all on the
same כוס. Kos. So you see it's the exact opposite of what
you said, not the need of separate ones but quite the opposite,
the assumption that you're going to do it all on the same
כוס. Kos. So what's the story, separate כוסות Kosot or the same
כוס? Kos? Says the גמרא, Gemara, אלא Ela here's the answer, הבדלה
וקידוש חדא מילתא היא. Havdalah Ve-Kiddush Chada Milta Hi. הבדלה Havdalah. and
קידוש Kiddush are the same thing. Now they're the same in the
fact that they're like diametrically opposite but they're doing the same idea,
they're distinguishing from holy and non-holy in different directions. Okay.
But ultimately they're defining the nature of the day and distinguishing it
from the previous days. So in that case, even though one is
working to from before and one is working going forward, nevertheless, they're
both about defining the nature of the day and you can therefore
incorporate them all in the same cup. But ברכת המזון וקידוש תרי
מילי נינהו, Birkat Hamazon v'Kiddush trei milei ninhu,
benching and Kiddush, those are conceptually completely different things or completely unrelated,
they're from different universes. One is about sanctifying and defining the day
and the other has to do with the fact that you ate
a meal. So therefore it'd be inappropriate to use the same cup
for both. Now this gets to this issue about reusing or not,
because here you see in the case of יקנה"ז, Yaknahaz, not only
are we allowing it, presumably we're even saying you should do it.
Bundle it up. The problem is that when it's conceptually a very
different type of a thing, then each one loses its identity if
you try to smoosh them together. If you try to combine a
ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon כוס kos with a קידוש Kiddush כוס, kos,
you don't know what you have here. It loses its identity. But
if it retains its identity, then maybe you're allowed or even required
to bundle them. Okay, so that's where we stop for now. We're
going to get to in a minute or tomorrow the issue of
the order יין Yayin קידוש Kiddush נר Ner, הבדלה, Havdalah but I
want to talk about this issue of חבילות חבילות chavilot chavilot in
terms of the חופה. chuppah. So if you take a look here
at
תוספות Tosafot שאין אומרים שתי קדושות על כוס אחד, she'ein omrim shtei
kadoshos al kos echad, תוספות Tosafot says ויש נוהגים בחופה v'yeish nohagim
bachuppah מטעם זה mita'am zeh שלא לומר שבע ברכות על כוס ברכת
המזון. shelo lomar Sheva Brachot al kos Birkat Hamazon. Now he's not
talking about under the חופה, chuppah, he means the meal after the
חופה. chuppah. That you don't say the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot on
the כוס ברכת המזון kos Birkat Hamazon because under the חופה chuppah
the כוס יין kos yayin is all about the שבע ברכות, Sheva
Brachot, but at the meal, the כוס יין kos yayin technically is
about the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon even for people who normally wouldn't
have a כוס יין kos yayin for ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So
that would be bundling two separate things together, ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
and שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. אלא מביאים כוס אחר ela mevi'im kos
acher ואין מברכין על השני בורא פרי הגפן. v'ein mevorchin al hasheini
Borei Pri HaGafen. So the first one you do בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen but not the second. כיון שכבר בירך על כוס
ברכת המזון, keivan shekvar beirach al kos Birkat Hamazon, דאין נכון לברך
פעמיים, d'ein nachon l'vareich pa'amayim, you shouldn't make a בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen twice. Now it's interesting because mostly this is what
we do. Does everybody ever see the whole magic they do with
the two כוסות? kosot? It's basically all because of this. I'm the
one leading benching, I say, I don't say בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri HaGafen yet, I want that to sort of come at the
end. It's interesting. תוספות Tosafot says כבר בירך בורא פרי הגפן. kvar
beirach Borei Pri HaGafen. It sounds like תוספות, Tosafot, and which makes
sense, I just finished benching, I'll say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri
HaGafen right now. Okay, so we say the בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri HaGafen later, but okay, I'm going to say בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen on this. Then we do, they take this כוס
kos around, everybody says their thing, da-da-da-da-da-da-da, bring it back. I'm going
to use my כוס kos to say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri
HaGafen. That's the כוס kos of benching. This is the כוס kos
of שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. And then we do the whole magic.
But it's really not such a magic. Basically, everybody wants, you want
to get everybody, the guy who's making the benching and the חתן
וכלה, chatan v'kallah, to have from both כוסות. kosot. So you pour
from these two into a third. That's now the mix of the
two, and from the third back into these two. So every כוס
kos has from the two כוסות. kosot. That's that whole business of
when you pour the whole thing. Anyway, that's all of that. Anyway,
it's all based on this of מצוות חבילות חבילות, mitzvot chavilot chavilot,
you don't want to bundle them up. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot says
אך רבינו משולם היה אומר הכל על כוס אחד. ach Rabbeinu Meshullam
hayah omer hakol al kos echad. He didn't do this whole thing.
He would do it all on one כוס. kos. דלא דמי לברכת
המזון וקידוש דתרי מילי נינהו. d'lo dami l'Birkat Hamazon v'Kiddush d'trei milei
ninhu. For this, for the case that we're dealing with, a weekday
meal, saying the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and the Kiddush, okay, those
are separate things כדאמרינן בסמוך, k'd'amrinan besamuch, והכא חדא
מילתא היא. v'hacha chada milta hi. The ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon גורם
goreim לברכת נישואין. l'virchas nisuin. Why are you doing שבע ברכות? Sheva
Brachot? You're doing שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot because you're having a meal.
So because the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot are connected to the meal
and are coming as a result of the meal and according to
some maybe were even established as part of the ברכת המזון, Birkat
Hamazon, that's why you're doing it. So it makes actually these are
very integrally connected and you can use one כוס, kos, maybe you
even should use one כוס. kos. So that's an interesting debate. We
don't do that, but that's a very persuasive position. Now he talks
about ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin under the חופה. chuppah. וברכת אירוסין ונישואין,
u'virchas eirusin u'nisuin, when we do it under the חופה, chuppah, נהגו
לומר על שתי כוסות. nahagu lomar al shtei kosos. You do it
on two separate כוסות. kosot. הטעם דהרגילים זה בלא זה, hata'am d'hergilim
zeh belo zeh, because often they would come separate, כדאמרינן בכתובות k'd'amrinan
bi'Kesuvos מברכין ברכת האירוסין mevorchin birchas ha'eirusin בבית אירוסין beveit eirusin וברכת
חתנים בבית חתנים. u'virchas chasanim beveit chasanim. Okay,
so it used to be that they would come separate times of
the year, you would have אירוסין eirusin a year before and different
locations, the house of the חתן chatan or the house of the
father-in-law, and therefore these are, although they are conceptually related, by God
they're all about getting married and they're all coming at the same
time, nevertheless in their origins they are very distinct types of ברכות.
brachot. וזה תוספות, v'zeh Tosafot, ועוד דנהגו לקרות כתובה בינתיים v'od d'nahagu
likros ketubah beintayim והוי הפסק v'havei hefsek ולכך נתכוונו. u'l'kach niskuvnu.
When you make the כתובה, ketubah, it's דווקא davka in order to,
like sort of like the whole שינוי מקום shinui makom idea, to
make a break and to say that this is something different. ולכך
נתכוונו, u'l'kach niskuvnu, and for that reason it's intentional. וכן צריך שתי
כוסות, v'chen tzarich shtei kosos, you can't use one כוס, kos, the
argument of using one כוס... kos... is that it's all sort of
it's all doing the same thing right now. So תוספות Tosafos says
when he says this conceptually is distinct. And it's interesting though, this
מנהג minhag of writing the כתובה ksuva because you could have still
have said, okay, but I used it, who cares? I used it
a week ago for אירוסין eirusin and I'll use it now for
נישואין, nisuin, it's fundamentally the same thing. So you see according to
תוספות Tosafos when you are allowed to bundle them and when it
is even when it's conceptually and thematically linked, it all needs to
be in the same experience. You need to be doing them as
it were all at the same time, like in one event. If
you're doing them at separate events, that by itself requires a separate
כוס. kos. Now, very often now, I think because people are just
afraid about spilling and whatnot what I see most of the time
is that they just slightly refill the כוס. kos. Okay, because you
have to anyway, if you drink from it you can't use the
כוס kos unless you add wine, it's considered פגום. pagum. But at
least the practice mostly I see is people do not have two
כוסות kosos under the חופה, chuppah, probably because you don't need to
get another thing to trip and make a mess and be concerned
about. But maybe some, maybe some still do. Okay, but this is
the issue about when do you דווקא davka combine, when do you
דווקא davka separate? And I do want to get back to Charlie's
question. I'll get back to you tomorrow about like why we דווקא
davka do combine ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon with שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos
when according to the גמרא Gemara you shouldn't. If you want to,
let's just start very briefly this next discussion about the יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz.
Okay, so let's take a look. We're going to have like five
different positions here about how to incorporate, oh my god, okay, how
to incorporate these things.
Well, it's very compelling to really urge two כוסות kosos under the
חופה. chuppah. Yeah. You find it compelling? Okay. Yeah, I do. It
resonates. Okay.
I find it more resonates to have only one כוס kos during
the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos meal. Wait, I felt the inspiration
I heard about the הבדלה havdalah wine for ברכת המזון, Birkas Hamazon,
right? That you're bringing the קדושה kedusha of שבת Shabbos into...
into the week. But the question again is how does it reconcile
itself with the הלכה halachic discussion here? Let's read just briefly these
opinions and then we'll continue this tomorrow. גופא, Gufa, יום טוב Yom
Tov שחל להיות אחר שבת. She-chal Lihyot Achar Shabbat. יום טוב Yom
Tov is after שבת Shabbos and you have to do benching and
you have to do הבדלה havdalah and קידוש kiddush all together and
with זמן, zman, with a שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. Or, well no, actually forget
it, we'll do with the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu part later. Without זמן, zman,
שביעי של פסח. Shvi'i shel Pesach.
רב אמר יקנ"ה, Rav amar Yakna, יין, yayin, קידוש, kiddush, נר, ner,
הבדלה. havdalah. As we said, by itself good, יין yayin and קידוש
kiddush by itself and then הבדלה havdalah by itself. The only question
is why קידוש kiddush before הבדלה. havdalah. So, you know the רשב"ם
Rashbam just says that,
if you take a look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, רב אמר יקנ"ה,
Rav amar Yakna, סבירא ליה קדושת היום עדיפא מהבדלה. s'vira lei kedushas
hayom adifa mehavdalah. If you want to emphasize one, you'd rather emphasize
the holiness of the day you're going into rather than the, you
know, rather than the fact that you're going, leaving a קדושה. kedusha.
So you want to sort of, you know, focus on that even
though chronologically it's out of order. אינמי דכי מבדיל ברישא מיחזי כדהויא
ליה קדושת היום כמשוי. Inami de-chi mavdil beresha michzei k'de-havya lei kedushas
hayom kemasuy.
This is an idea we have very often that when you have
orders of things, you should do הבדלה havdalah later because you want
to show like when on חנוכה Chanukah you do הבדלה havdalah in
שול, shul, so obviously you wait till שבת Shabbos is out, but
first you light נר חנוכה ner Chanukah and then you do the
הבדלה, havdalah, although that's ironic, you can't light נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah,
you know, while it's still שבת, Shabbos, but nevertheless you want to
show how you're reluctant to do the הבדלה, havdalah, so even if
it's just a minute you push it off a little bit to
demonstrate that reluctance. Again, ironic because you're already doing the קדושה kedusha
which is in a way introducing the next day, but ending שבת
Shabbos and introducing the next day. Right. Anyway, so that's רב. Rav.
רב Rav says קידוש kiddush comes before
הבדלה. havdalah. דשמואל אמר ינה"ק. de-Shmuel amar Yanhak. So שמואל Shmuel says
no, I gotta tell you I like שמואל Shmuel better. יין, yayin,
נר, ner, הבדלה, havdalah, you do the full הבדלה, havdalah, again, oh
I forgot to mention
why no בשמים, besamim, and then you do
the קידוש, kiddush, thank you. So you do הבדלה havdalah and then
קידוש. kiddush. Okay. And now we're going to see tomorrow about five
more possibilities. You can actually, you know, figure out how many logical
possibilities, right? What is it? If there's four of them it's 4x3x2,
there's 24 logical possibilities, we're only going to have about six or
seven of them. Anyway, but why I want to set-, I'll end
by saying why nobody is talking about בשמים. besamim. So the רשב"ם
Rashbam says with no בשמים besamim because because because because
you have a נשמה יתירה neshama yeseira also on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, and therefore you don't need בשמים besamim because there's you-, and
you know the whole idea of בשמים besamim is you lose your
נשמה יתירה neshama yeseira and you need the בשמים besamim to revive
you. And that's why you don't do it. תוספות Tosafos says no,
that can't be, because if the same idea of נשמה יתירה neshama
yeseira applied on יום טוב, Yom Tov, then every הבדלה havdalah from
מוצאי יום טוב motzei Yom Tov you should have to use בשמים.
besamim. So it's not that you have a נשמה יתירה, neshama yeseira,
this idea on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but you do have, you
do have שמחה simcha of יום טוב Yom Tov and the שמחה
simcha of יום טוב Yom Tov is enough to sort of support
you with that loss of the נשמה יתירה, neshama yeseira, so you
don't need the בשמים besamim to do that function. The fact that
you're entering into the שמחה simcha of יום טוב Yom Tov gives
you enough sort of חיזוק, chizuk, you know, gives you enough revival
that you don't need the בשמים besamim and that's why we do
not have בשמים besamim during the יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz. have בשמים Besomim when
we go from in this scenario when we go from שבת Shabbos
to יום טוב. Yom Tov. We make קידוש, Kiddush, we make נר,
Ner, but we don't. Why do you make נר? Ner? Because נר
Ner is about fire and creativity, I can discuss נר Ner a
little bit more, but anyway נר Ner is allowed on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, not allowed on שבת, Shabbos, so that is a clear
divider. But בשמים Besomim is not needed and therefore we don't have
בשמים. Besomim. So right now we have the debate of רב Rav
and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav says you do the קידוש Kiddush part
first, שמואל Shmuel says you do the הבדלה Havdala part first. We
will see more positions about this tomorrow.